<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Mayor</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843403</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843403</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 476:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Mayor</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Day,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1576]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: the xviii yeare of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth [i.e. 1576].</note>
                  <note>Orders directing all commodities to be sold only in the public market--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Markets --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8134:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the Mayor.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas not onely of Common vſage and auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome vſed within this honorable Citie, But alſo of &amp; by the olde lawes &amp; ordinaunces made and executed in the ſame Citie it is manifeſt That all manner of Commodities, Clothes and Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dizes made and wrought within the kyngdome of England and dominions of the ſame, brought vnto the ſayd Citie to be ſold, were and ought to be brought vnto ſuche common market places as to that purpoſe within the ſame Citie was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, And there onely and not els where ought to be bought and ſold, And the owners therof did there pay Halladge and other duties, whiche was ſo done as well that good and lawfull wares ſhould be bought and ſold &amp; corrupt and vnlawfull bargaynes and contractes tending to the deceite of the people, &amp; contrary to the lawes of the Realme might be auoyded: As alſo that there might be no forreyne bying and ſellyng in fraude of the liberties, francheſies, and cuſtomes of the ſayd Citie being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed &amp; ratyfied by act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And where of late yeares dyuers ſortes of Cloth and other Commodityes and marchandizes ſome of wolle onely, and ſome of wollen and lynen wouen together haue bene and are dayly made &amp; wrought within this realme and the dominions therof and dayly and from tyme are brought to this Citie there to be ſold, And becauſe they are not called by any of the ſame names that the clothes of Wollen or Lynen of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer auncyent tyme were (although they conſiſte of the ſame ſubſtance) The makers and marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of pretend a libertie to themſelues to make their markets therof, and to buy and ſell the ſame in Innes, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and warehouſes and all other partes of this Citie and Liberties therof at their pleaſure, Aſwell in the great deceite of many her Maieſties louing Subiectes, and more eaſye vtteraunce of naughtye and deceyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wares: As alſo to the redier and more eaſye intruding vpon the liberties of this Citie by forren bying and ſellyng: Therfore in remedye of the ſayd diſorders, The Lord Mayor and his worſhypfull brethren thalder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the common counſell of this Citie now aſſembled do ordeyne and enact, That from henceforth all manner of clothes of newe deuiſe, commodities and marchaundizes aforeſayd made of wolle or of wollen &amp; lynen together (not accuſtomed heretofore to be brought to Blackwellhall, which hereafter ſhalbe brought to this Citie to be ſolde, ſhall be wholy brought to the common market place named the waſted halle ſituate at the Northend of thold Iurye in the ward of Baſſinghall within this Citie, And there from henceforth ſhalbe bought and ſolde and not elſewhere within the liberties of the ſame Citie, And that no perſon or perſons free of this Citie or any other dwelling within the liberties therof, or hauing any houſe ſhop or romyth within the ſame Citie or liberties therof ſhall from henceforth there or elſwhere within the ſame libertyes take in, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, harbor or beſtowe, or ſuffer to be taken in, receyued, harbored, or beſtowed, any of the ſayd clothes of newe deuiſe, Commodities or Marchandizes before the ſame be brought to the market place aforeſaid ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appoynted and there harbored, taken in, bought and ſolde.</p>
            <p>And by authoritie aforeſayd it is enacted and ordayned that the markets for the ſayd clothes of new deuiſe commodities and marchandizes aforeſayd ſhall and may be from henceforth weekely had and kept in the hall or market place aforeſayd euery Teweſday &amp; Wedneſday fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viii. vntill xi. of the clocke in the forenoone, and from one vntil foure of the clocke in the afternoone. And it is further ordained by authoritie aforeſayd, That from henceforth the officers of the ſayd hall and market place or ſome of them ſhalbe attendaunt at the ſayd hall to receaue the premiſſes from tyme to tyme, who ſhall and may take for hallage &amp; and other char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the ſayd Clothes of new deuiſe, commodities, and marchandizes ſuch rates for ſuch tyme and in ſuch ſorte as followeth. That is to ſay:
<list>
                  <item>Narrow Raſhe for Doblytting conteyning xxx. yeardes the doble peece, for hallage. j. d.</item>
                  <item>Brode Raſhe for Clokes and other garmentes conteyning from <hi>20.</hi> to <hi>25.</hi> yeardes the peece. ij. d.</item>
                  <item>Borratoſe wrought with ſilk conteining vnder <hi>20</hi> yeardes ob. and the doble peece aboue <hi>25.</hi> yeardes. i. d.</item>
                  <item>Plomites wrought with ſilke or otherwiſe the ſingle peece, ob. and the doble peece. i. d.</item>
                  <item>Carrels conteining xiiii. yeardes a peece one farthing.</item>
                  <item>Worſted hoſe the dozen payre. ii. d.</item>
                  <item>Norwhich gartryng the groſſe. ob.</item>
                  <item>Stowle lace and penny bredth lace the dozen groſſe i. d.</item>
                  <item>Crewell or worſted yearne the dozen pound i. d.</item>
                  <item>Friu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>re the dozen pound weight i. d.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8134:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t when as the halladge and other dueties according to the rates aforeſayd ſhalbe payd, the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer or his d putye in that caſe appoynted ſhall ſtrike a ſeale of lead vpon euery particuler peece of the ſayd marchaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>izes aſwell in diſcharge of the owner from any redemaund thereof, as alſo to charge the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he mony receaued. And bycauſe in experience not onlye towching the laſt recyted premiſſes but alſo towching diuers auncient ſortes of Cloth, diuers diſorders are dayly committed: It is alſo by auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye aforeſayd ordeyned that if any of the premiſſes aunciently made or of new deviſe or heareafter to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed &amp; made within this Realme and dominions thereof ſhalbe brought to this Cittie to be ſould, That the ſame ſeuerally ſhalbe brought to the ſayd ſeuerall markets and there to be harbored and not els where till the ſame be firſt bought &amp; ſold within one of the ſame markets. And that if any of the premiſſes ſhalbe bought in the Countrye by any former bergayne by any freeman of this Cittie and after brought heither that the ſame or a trew certificate therof ſhalbe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted at ſuch of the ſayd halls as apperteineth as aforſayd And the hallage therefore payd or a bill therefore geuen by the ſame freeman to the ordinarye officer before the ſame ſhalbe receyued or harbored vpon payne that euery freeman and forreine dwelling in this Cittie or the liberties therof which ſhall receyue or harbor any of the premiſſes otherwiſe or contrary to the trew mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ordinaunces aforeſayd ſhall forfeyt &amp; pay to thuſe of the cominaltie of this Cittie for euery broade Cloth ſo harbored vi. s viii. d. for euery kerſey iii. s. iiii. d. for euery Bridgewater xx. d. and for euery other of the auncient wollen clothes accordingly in an equal rate for euery worſted iii s. iiii. d. for euery tuffed mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ado xx. d. and for euery other of the premiſſes of new deuiſe now being or heareafter to be accordingly in an equall rate and for auoyding all pretence of excuſe that the premiſſes ſhalbe forthwith publikely proclaymed. All which penalties &amp; forfeytures to be incurred by force of the ſayd ordinaunces, ſhalbe recouered by actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of debt, bill, playnt, or information, to be brought or exhibeted &amp; purſued in the Queenes maieſties court in the vtter Chamber of the Guildhall of this Cittie of London commonly called the mayors court by and in the name of the Chamberlayne of this Cittie for the tyme being. And all ſommes of money and forfeytures ſo to be recouered ouer &amp; aboue the charges of the ſute, ſhalbe imployed in forme following. That is to ſay, one third part to thuſe of the Mayor &amp; comminaltye &amp; Cittyze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this Cittie, the one other third part to the reliefe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore in Chriſtes hoſpitall in this Cittie, and the other third part to ſuch perſons as ſhall preſent &amp; geue infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſuch offence and doe his diligence that the offender may be duely conuicted. And for that no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſon or perſons ſhall heareafter excuſe themſelues for lack of warning, neither be ignoraunt of the foreſayd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd rates aboue recited My ſayd Lord M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>or and his right worſhipfull brethren thaldermen haue thought good by publique proclamation to thend to take away aſmuch as in them lieth all ſuch fayned &amp; vntrew allegations &amp; excuſes openly to publiſh and proclayme the ſayd law and ordinaunce that the ſame may be obſerued accordingly. Yeuen at the Guildehall of this honorable Citie of London this preſent xxviii. of October in the xviii. yeare of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Day.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
